Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): hello somebody my name is daylin uh i am a writer activist and voice actor out of seattle i've got a passion for pop culture witty retorts and unlocking the adult potential that comes with healing from childhood trauma that's my thing um alongside me i have
Speaker 2: aj aj who are you i am a historical scavenger hunter let's go
Speaker 2: - A systems
Speaker 3: agitator. - Talk about it. - And a proponent of all things that black women do well, which is everything. - Well now.
- And
Speaker 3: here at Battle Fatigue, we want to create a space that allows black people to know and remember that there is no wrong way for you to be black. Your black is beautiful and your black is
Speaker 4: accepted.
Speaker 5: - And valid and right
Speaker 6: and okay. And on a spectrum of which you deserve to be able to explore along.
Speaker 3: So we hope that you enjoy a little bit of who we are in this episode where we honor the late Chadwick Boseman and the impact that he has had on our friendship. And then we get into the what I call scary mess that is love. It's perfection. Yeah, you call
it whatever
Speaker 3: you want to call it. That's perfection. Whatever. That is Lovecraft Country and the brilliance that...
Speaker 3: comes with black people being able to get big budget money and do whatever
Speaker 8: black people do best, which is create.
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): - Yeah. So please enjoy. Also, thank you very much to Senator Turner for allowing us to kind of
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): sneak in the back door and show you a little bit of what we're about and because we support her and everything that she stands for and what her words
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): are and how meaningful they are and how impactful her career has been. So Senator DeTerno, we thank you
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and we honor you. And now for a little
bit of
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): battle fatigue.
Speaker 11: Go black women. Okay, let's start
with the racism.
i mean we are about to talk
Speaker 12: about lovecraft country
Speaker 13: you're going to talk about lovecraft country so
Speaker 14: yeah yeah so on august 28th we were uh honoring
Speaker 15: the great many moments um that took place in the story arc of blackness yeah i just i had finished like facilitating a class i went to go get ice cream because i needed it
And
Speaker 17: then on my way back from getting ice cream, I was getting like a bunch of text messages from people being
Speaker 15: like, "Are you okay?" And I was like, "I don't, I mean, thank you. "The session wasn't that hard, but like, "thank you for your concern." And then my best friend Julian was like, "You need to check like social."
And I
Speaker 17: was like, "Okay." And then I looked and I saw like Chadwick Boseman, the King T'Challa had
Speaker 15: passed.
Speaker 19: yeah at
Speaker 15: like the age of 43 and i was like no this is a hoax and
then i
Speaker 15: was like let me let me do the google because if if it's on news websites then it's like okay this shit's real and i remember like i just parked my car and the very first person i was like i need to
Speaker 20: call i need to call sultan because i don't know if he knows and i don't know if like people are texting
Speaker 2: him but i was like i need to call sultan they
Speaker 21: were and um i was getting text i was driving
Like it
Speaker 21: wasn't, you know, the phone wasn't hooked up to Bluetooth and I didn't want to like put the phone on and
Speaker 22: all that kind of stuff. Because we are safety first all the time. Right. And also because we're
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): black. Yeah, that's the reason. So, yeah, I ignored the call, but it's in like a little quick little one-handed text. I was like, hey.
I'm going to
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): call you when I park. I'm driving, yeah, I'll call you when I park. And then you texted me, and I'm glad I didn't see that text until I parked because you just decided. Yeah, well, sorry. To just.
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): I was in shock. Just the napalm text. Was it because it was a screenshot, right? It was a picture. Yeah, yeah. It was a picture of the news showing that he had passed, 43.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): And I was parked, and I saw it, and my, everything blurred.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): everything just
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): blurred and everything went silent i don't even think my heart was beating you know it and
then we
Speaker 28: talked
Speaker 29: we
Speaker 31: did
Speaker 31: - You called back, I was still sitting in my car, like I had parked in my
Speaker 15: parking spot back in my apartment and my friend Charles or my brother mentor, I don't know, black people, we don't have titles for people in our lives, just positions. Charles
Speaker 17: had sent me a text and all he wrote was, "Are you serious, Chadwick Boseman?" And I was like, what did he do? Like what did T'Challa do now? Or like what movie is T'Challa about to be in or like
Speaker 32: something.
Speaker 32: And then I got Julian's text and I was like, um, I don't understand. And part of the reason that we want to start the show with this
Speaker 33: before we get into the mess that is Love, Care, Country is because Black Panther, the movie, holds a very special space in our lives.
Speaker 33: friendship
Speaker 34: yes so a
Speaker 33: very cliff notes origin story uh sultan and i met because of a mutual person that we know um and then we uh ended up realizing that like we actually really like talking to each other
um
Speaker 35: and then we became
friends um
Speaker 35: and it all started off with like comic books because
Speaker 17: for black folks it's sometimes really
Speaker 15: difficult to find
um
Speaker 15: other black people who love and know comics as much as you do. And so when we discovered our mutual love of like all things comic books and nerd minus horror, because F that, we'll get to that in a second. Then I was like, oh, this is gonna be like a really awesome friendship. And I've said this many times before, I just like listening to you talk. So I was like, if I can be your
Speaker 3: friend and have opportunities to listen to you talk.
And I
Speaker 3: think at the time you were still performing slam poetry.
Speaker 36: Are there friendships where the opportunity to hear someone talk
Speaker 32: doesn't exist?
Speaker 15: Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I think I have strictly text message. Okay, we're like strictly social media friends like we don't talk on the phone, but once I realized that you are a a
Speaker 15: - A plethora of talents. - A
Speaker 37: plethora of talents, okay. -
I
Speaker 33: was like, I want to keep him in my life in any way that I can. And then Black Panther was gonna come out, which we first saw him in Civil War.
And I
Speaker 33: was like, ooh,
Speaker 38: okay.
Speaker 17: Because I kind of knew of Chadwick Boseman. I was like, okay, 42, Thurgood Marshall, whatever. But he wasn't on my radar like that.
Speaker 39: mainly because i don't really like watching movies about bad shit happening to black people um because i live bad shit happening to black
Speaker 17: people every day i
Speaker 40: am the movie
and so you know obviously like
Speaker 17: marvel the movies were coming out and then when we got to civil war like it was like okay yeah this
Speaker 33: is major look at these kicks
Speaker 33: and then all of a sudden t'challa comes in and you're like hold up okay chadwick yeah what are the shoulder muscles
Speaker 41: called shoulder
Speaker 17: muscles okay yeah those um with the traps thank you i should know that considering that i definitely think that's your
Speaker 42: twitter handle um and then his neck was looking all buff with a little like choker necklace
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): thing yeah he he was he was lifting with chains around his neck
Speaker 15: he was he definitely was i think he was doing that jaw muscle exercise
Speaker 43: too
yeah
Speaker 15: But either way, I was like, okay, so we're not about to have, like, a corny black superhero.
Speaker 33: This is about to be, like, the shit. And then Black Panther, the movie, came out. Michael B. Fine played Killmonger. And, I mean, you could do the Google
Speaker 15: and all the historical points that they were really key on. But we were like, we're going to go see this.
Speaker 32: Yeah, we're seeing that. And then we went to South Center. We did. And we got into a line. We
Speaker 46: got into a line, like, waiting to see the movie as there were other—no, no, we were the first. We were—
Speaker 46: We were the first, there were some other kids that were kind of hanging out. -
Speaker 15: Yup, and we were excited. And we were just talking and stuff. And then as we, as like the line started to,
you know,
Speaker 15: move up to let us in, we realized we were not in the line that we were supposed to be in. We were in the
Speaker 47: like, this is for
Speaker 17: special VIP people line. - Yeah. - And then this like really couldn't care less attitude of a person handed us these like commemorative coins. - Yeah.
And
Speaker 17: then was like, you
Speaker 39: can make your way into the theater.
Speaker 48: - Then we got to
Speaker 39: go in, yeah. - And then we watched it and it was as magical as we expected it to be, if not more. - Oh my God,
what
Speaker 49: an amazing film.
Speaker 50: - And I remember just, I remember being like, oh my, oh my,
Speaker 47: this is us, this is what film could be when black people
Speaker 17: are just given
want
Speaker 17: Disney money
Speaker 51: just leave us alone and let us and let us do this work let us let us be the magic
Speaker 17: yeah don't put any restraints on us don't put any of your whiteness on us and
Speaker 32: just let us be and then we got the magic that is black panther
Speaker 52: the film and ever since
Speaker 53: that day when we got
Speaker 15: our coins
We
Speaker 15: would do something that we called a coin check. Coin check. And we would just send each other pictures, which Sultan did this morning, and I forgot because
Speaker 55: today's Monday, and I don't fully come to life until about 1.35 p.m.
Speaker 56: Tuesday. I
want to feel like it's an
Speaker 57: attack, but it's so real.
You're such a
Speaker 57: jerk.
Speaker 17: The news of the death of T'Challa hit us a little differently than
Speaker 58: other folks. And, you know, the tributes have been coming in, which I personally am not ready to read.
Speaker 59: I've seen a few. I've read, you know, some of the ones that came from his co-stars, of course,
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): and from Ryan Coogler. Ryan Coogler, who wasn't even he wasn't even sure that he wanted to do Black Panther, you know, work kind of work with Chagabot until he saw the scene
Man 60: in Civil War of him and his father.
He
Man 60: said he saw that scene and kind of watched them work together and watched how, you know, just the poise that Chadwick kind of, you know, presented as, you know, as T'Challa. And that's when he knew. That's
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): when he's like, yeah, we're doing this.
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): Chagel Boseman is an incredible actor, an incredible human being, but for
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): what he was a part of him, the way that he was able to kind of put blackness on the forefront in a way that like for children and adults alike, that just motivated and energized and gave so much life to, I saw the movie like five times in a theater.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): with no regrets. Such a moment and such a movement around the world, and then to be up there in the
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): top ten films domestically, you know, with franchises
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): like Star Wars. Representation matters 1,000%. And this movie proves
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): that. And a lot of other shows do, a lot of other movies do, but in the way that this one, just around the world,
just...
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): showed and proved how much representation matters you know there was that one segment on jimmy fallon where oh yeah where like jimmy was in the back with with chadwick and then they had the poster and
they had
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): black people come in with like their families you know children parents you know individual folks and just hey we just want you to talk about what black panther
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): meant to you
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): and it was this long segment and of course it's been making this you know rotation again and um oh
Speaker 63: and then
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): he comes out he comes
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): out to to meet them and everybody loses their mind because it's they don't see chadwick boseman they see representation they see black panther they see the movement they see they see everything that that film and
Speaker 64: what he did in that film what they see the definition of that to them in
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): him that's what he was able to bring
and
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): and and he just happened to be called Chadwick Boseman
Speaker 65: you know what
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): yeah oh yeah yeah you know it is what it is but I say that I grew up in Charleston yeah that's why I was like
Speaker 67: I can't know that's actually stand up I guess I'm your kin
Speaker 21: yeah yeah he paved the way for
Speaker 21: Watchmen, he helped pave the way for
Speaker 68: Lovecraft Country.
Speaker 69: God, Lovecraft Country, are you kidding me? - Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. I have a curious question for you before
Speaker 70: we, but also that was a
Speaker 3: really nice segue. I'm sorry to like mess up.
Speaker 32: - No, you're good. - So a friend of mine asked me this question
and I
Speaker 32: didn't know how to answer the question and anytime I don't know how to answer a question, I usually ask you the same question to see if you can come up with a
Speaker 33: better answer or an answer at all.
Speaker 33: That's what friendship is. So do you think that the response to that we are having to the
Speaker 17: death of T'Challa would be the same if it was Michael B. Jordan who passed?
And I
Speaker 17: ask that because people obviously are talking about the body of work that Chadwick has done and how specific it is to black history. And also, obviously, I've never heard of a story of Michael B. Jordan being a jerk to somebody. But there's
Speaker 33: something intangible about Chadwick. Because people are like, our king is dead, right? Would they be like, Killmonger is dead, you know?
Speaker 33: Or would it just be like, oh, it's Michael B. Jordan? And I think the, yeah.
- This goes
Speaker 72: along the lines of the whole representation thing.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): No, I don't think that the impact would be the same or greater. It would be sad. And, you know, of course folks would, you know, look at his works and look at perhaps what he's done, you know, in like the humanitarian field, philanthropically, you know, that kind
of thing.
And
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): maybe there'll be some hashtags. Killmonger was right.
But that
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): line was actually because of Chadwick.
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah. Well, maybe not the line, but just the
Speaker 74 (lower-pitched voice): idea that because originally he was they were going to have him request to be buried in Wakanda. And then Chadwick was like, would
Man 60: he do that? Yeah.
Speaker 26 (lower-pitched voice): because that yeah that that pride and resentment yeah um which is real so deep in his core yeah yeah would he want to be built buried in wakama yeah i'll kill my daddy no yeah exactly um
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): no i don't think that it would be because of the role that chadwick played also um the previous roles
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): That he played, you know, being Jackie
Speaker 75: Robinson, Thurgood Marshall, James Brown.
Speaker 76: He's about to be in Ma Rainey's. He's going to be in Ma Rainey's.
Speaker 77: Something or other,
Speaker 76: Black something.
Speaker 78: Black
Speaker 77: Bottom? Black Bottom. Yeah. So, yeah, Chadwick, he was
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): Jackie Robinson, Thurgood Marshall. He was James Brown and Black Panther. He's going to be in Ma Rainey's Black Bottom.
-
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): The Five Bloods, you know, just-- - Damn.
Speaker 64: Plank, he, my man did, what, six, seven movies?
-
Speaker 80: Ooh, all while he was sick.
Speaker 81: Action movies while he was sick, you know? - Where he had to like gain weight, lose weight, gain weight, lose weight.
- Yeah. -
Speaker 81: That's, and on a compromised immune system, that's insane.
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): - Yeah, yeah. But all to say, no, I don't think that it would be the same just because a
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): lot of people look at overall impact
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): um they look at the impact and while kim monger is an impactful character yeah it's not the same
level of
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): representation the rebel of level of energy and impact that black panther
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): yeah had also a lot of people kind of scoff it uh michael b jordan's acting prowess and you know a lot of
Speaker 85: times even though i mean he can act but i think
Speaker 86: we just don't talk about fantastic
Speaker 85: four we and see yeah yeah yeah so so no that
Speaker 87: that puts a dent in his which i don't even
Speaker 87: necessarily think he did a bad job i think there's just a fantastic four movie was just horrible yeah
yeah
Speaker 88: yeah yeah that's
it yeah
Speaker 88: just yeah because i mean
Speaker 87: he was absolutely
Speaker 17: brilliant in fruitvale station
Speaker 89: yeah so
Speaker 17: you can't so you think okay all right yeah and then he just gets some roles that you're like you don't maybe the person doesn't know how to direct
Speaker 32: him or perhaps you know whatever but anyway i just wanted
Speaker 90: to i wanted
to uh
I wanted
Speaker 90: to ask that question and also just to give us an opportunity to honor Chadwick in the way that he Has
Speaker 55: been part of our friendship Because also that was that was difficult that
Speaker 15: was yeah, that was some shit it was um and Onto some more shit. We need to talk about Lovecraft Country one
Charles James
Speaker 15: Douglas the third This is your fault that I'm watching Lovecraft Country and having the bejesus scared out of me every Sunday to
Speaker 15: Magnolia was a Sun downtown and that's
Speaker 31: the area that Charles lives in so I try to watch the show really really early so that I can leave so that the Sun don't catch me so Sun don't catch me over there so four episodes of Lovecraft are out right now and
Speaker 33: Lovecraft is Misha Green who was also
I
Speaker 33: think the writer, creator of Underground, which Journey
Speaker 15: Smollett was in. And then one of the executive producers of Lovecraft is Mr. Jordan Peele. And premise
of
Speaker 33: Lovecraft Country, which Sultan, I'm going to need your help
Speaker 15: with this. Basically, it's this book by this dude named Matt Ruff, which I believe was published in 2016. And it's based off of the kind of world of
a...
Speaker 15: really
Speaker 3: really racist man named h.p lovecraft who was a sci-fi writer who died i think when he was like 46 in obscurity but then his books all of a
Speaker 15: sudden like picking up steam because racism and he wrote a famous or infamous poem called on the backs of n-words um and that pretty much
Speaker 17: tells you all you need to know about h.p lovecraft um that's it we're good he also despised jewish people basically he despised anybody that wasn't white and he
Speaker 15: thought that Hitler
Speaker 15: um was a clown but also i believe and i quote he said he's a clown but also i really like that boy right so if you were ever curious about hp lovecraft there it is the interesting thing about lovecraft
Speaker 17: country which i think is probably the only reason i can really watch it without completely like peeing on myself every five seconds is because it is just like it's history like for black people watching it at least for me personally watching it i'm like oh this is what like a Tuesday is for a black person. Um,
Speaker 17: And I think because there's so many historical ties in the show, it's a little easier for me to stomach. So there are
Speaker 3: going to be spoilers. We're trying to keep it light. We're going to be jumping in and out of the episodes. And we will be saying some stuff that you probably didn't want to know if you don't like spoilers. If you do like spoilers, stick
Speaker 15: around, chum. Or if
Speaker 96: you don't care. Or if
Speaker 15: you don't care. Yeah, if this is not your cup of tea, which it's not mine, but I have to watch it.
I
Speaker 15: feel like we need
to
Speaker 97: sage before we start talking
about
Speaker 98: this. You need to sage. I'm fine. This is why I need
to be in a
Speaker 98: relationship so I can have somebody to snuggle with.
Speaker 22: Love, craft, country. I think the best thing about this show is that I get
to
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): see black people live their life in a way that's expected.
and
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): also unexpected you know given the the supernatural the paranormal parts of parts of the show um and also the the event the action adventure thriller you know dramatic parts as well that usually when we watch film and tv shows we know
Speaker 21: it's like well we would never do that like girl what you doing like that that whole thing yeah but in this show it's so different Because I watch them and all of those thoughts and all those
Speaker 64: feelings are just
completely
Speaker 64: gone in a race and i'm just like where we going next what's what's the next
Speaker 77: heist where we going turn left turn right what's good and meanwhile i'm like no no no i can't wait i cannot wait to watch what
Speaker 64: these black people do and be successful at because it defies so many of the things that we don't
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): do like um like swimming like being involved with monsters reading yeah facing down racism um Moving the white, pioneering, going, exploring, going on these heists like underground.
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): and episode
Speaker 22: four was kind of that that indiana jenkins slash juneys episode
Speaker 100: i can't stand you i was not gonna say
Speaker 101: the black indiana jones get on my nerves he
Speaker 102: goes by indy
into
Speaker 31: jinx yeah and then the interesting like foreshadowing right because like in episode four there's a little boy who's in the library he's reading journey to the center of
Speaker 15: the earth and then later and then later like atticus or tick um who plays who's played by jonathan majors who my god yeah first
of
Speaker 103: all they
Speaker 15: picked a really
Speaker 17: good person who you could tell like i don't know how he just is a really good actor because he acts as though he was like an awkward kid and like grew up in that grew
Speaker 31: into his body and still is very much so the awkward kid which i was like
Speaker 31: like this is brilliant and then you see him in real life and you're like oh sir there's not a bit awkward about you
Speaker 104: um i also like that black women particularly uh letty is like she saves them over and over and over and over again yeah which is the story of like black women right saving shit facts but she is complicated she is um absolutely brilliant journey journey smollett was made for this character yeah i just i i
Speaker 104: I truly appreciate it. Also, I like the history that they weave into it. In the first episode, when they are like driving, we see the Gordon Parks image. Actually, Gordon Parks imagery is all over that first
Speaker 15: episode and also there's like the voice, which we see most of them during the voiceover of James Baldwin when he was having the debate with
Speaker 106: William Buckley. - When we, the Americans, we, the American
Speaker 108: people, are able to accept the fact
that
Speaker 108: I have to accept, for example, that my ancestors are both white
and black,
Speaker 108: that on that continent we are trying to forge a new identity for which we need each other,
and that
Speaker 108: I am not a ward of America. I am not an object of missionary charity. I am one of the people who built the country. Until this moment, there is scarcely any hope for the American
dream.
Because
Speaker 108: the people who are denied participation in it,
by their
Speaker 108: very presence,
will
Speaker 109: wreck it. And
if that
Speaker 109: happens, it's a very grave moment for the West. Thank you. And
we also
Speaker 110: need to note that
Speaker 104: the year is 1955. Yes.
Speaker 111: Yes.
This
Speaker 104: is 1955 prior to the murder of Emmett Till because I believe it was episode three that we realized
Speaker 17: that one of the little boys that Uncle George's daughter Dee was playing with was Emmett Till because he had on the white shirt and the tie that we see in the picture that most people show of Emmett Till
Speaker 112: prior to his death. With the stripe. With
Speaker 35: the stripe.
Speaker 35: And they also call him Bobo. Yes. And so it was like a hot second that I was like, hold up, did they just? And then like everything clicked and I was like, oh, you sons of bitches.
Speaker 113: Yeah. What in the shared universe
Speaker 115: is this?
But here's another
Speaker 21: thing. Did you catch that
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): the other boy, his name was Gil? And there's some talk that that might be Gil Scott Heron.
Speaker 116: oh son of a biscuit whose
Speaker 117: poem we heard in episode two oh my
Speaker 118: gosh stop
Speaker 117: okay okay okay
Speaker 119: all right excuse me hello somebody
Speaker 118: excuse me why
are you
Speaker 120: like
Speaker 30: this
-
Speaker 120: Why are you
Speaker 30: pulling me out of my Monday blues? Stop pulling,
Speaker 104: look I even wore blue today. Yeah, the deep cuts, especially for a history nerd like me, is like what is helping me get through
Speaker 121: the scary parts. And boy, are there some scary parts.
-
Speaker 46: This even, 'cause even down to the Safe Negro Travel Guide, which is basically the Green Book.
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): And which was originally called, I think the Negro Motorist
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): Green Book, right? Negro Motors Green Book? Yeah. For, like, 30
Speaker 21: years, this was, like, the travel guide for black folks. Like, you didn't leave home without it. Hell no. And it initially started from Victor Hugo Green. Yep. He...
Speaker 21: he uh create he was a postal worker which
Speaker 77: it kind of makes sense
Speaker 123: the USPS yeah save
Speaker 77: the USPS please um he he was a he was a postal worker who um and it makes
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): sense that he would that this
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): would come from somebody that whose job was to travel in and out of like these restaurants and these gas stations and neighborhoods and know what's safe what's not safe and which means that my man had to be quite the observant like the astute observant person like the profiler to know
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): between where the black-owned companies were and also were the ones that just were non-discriminatory. And to put all those
Speaker 126: together. And that's probably the real dangerous one, is just being like, are y'all...
Speaker 17: Yeah, because I think in the first episode, Uncle George is like, oh, I got a tip for a location that I need to go check out. Right, right. And with the...
Speaker 17: like actual Green Book, the non Lovecraft Green Book, you know, Mr. Green would get tips from other postal workers also from around the country because, you know, one thing that's really necessary for us to understand as far as history is like, it wasn't just the South that was racist. The whole country was racist. And part of the reason I mentioned, you know, Charles's neighborhood is like Magnolia here in Seattle was a sundown town. So this idea that racism, you know,
Speaker 17: was only in the south
part of
Speaker 17: the reason you needed a green book was because when you went up north you still needed to know what parts were safe versus the south where it's like it was pretty blatant there were signs you knew where you could and could not go but then in an area like a seattle in an area like you know chicago you needed to know
what
Speaker 39: areas of that city were safe enough for you to travel and that's where the green book would come in handy right it was at the you know very much uh danger
Speaker 4: of the people who were collecting that
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): information right and eventually
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah. And the book just continued expanding. Yeah.
Speaker 132: Which is why I'm a little upset at the movie, The Green Book, because it was not even about the Green Book. But anyway.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah.
Speaker 133: Because white people.
Speaker 134: Isn't that fun? Story of our lives. Anyway. Green Book is real Monday. It's
a real Monday movie. Yeah.
- I'm just gonna
Speaker 135: laugh
Speaker 136: through this.
Speaker 17: What has been your favorite episode so far, you think? Or like the one that maybe shook you the most or the scene or the whatever?
Speaker 46: - I think probably episode four. The kind of Goonies episode, Indiana Jenkins. Just because
Speaker 21: that kind of spoke to the kid at heart.
Speaker 21: I don't think there's anything in that show that where they come across a situation and they're like, nah, why would I do that? You know, black people don't or there's no there's nothing negative. There's nothing like black people can't do this or black people don't do that. Or why would I ever do that?
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): They just go forward and they're smart about it. I'm a bit emotional about it, you know, at times because, you know, there's still that whole.
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): um that like man has to be a man thing
Speaker 138: let he stay home thing and it's like fam have you not seen me the last three episodes like i don't understand yeah i wish she'd break the fourth wall and
Speaker 139: be like i episode one through three like what what do you want more than you need yeah but um you know so
Speaker 140: they get the line when he's like girl you don't roll over this car
my
Speaker 141: name's not girl
i'm
Speaker 142: sorry mom she said it first quoting
we're
Speaker 143: just quoting yeah it doesn't it doesn't count as cussing if you're quoting i think that that that episode wait
Speaker 15: pause white people don't don't use that to say the n-word just i just yes yeah you can't say it cannot
Speaker 74 (lower-pitched voice): speak to what you do in the car with your windows up but with your windows
down you won't get
Speaker 74 (lower-pitched voice): got our
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): ears are working um
That
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): episode, I think, is supposed to be because it just... The amount
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): of the ability and just how strong they were as a team, in spite the issues that were happening amongst the three of them, between Tick and Letty and between Tick and his father. -
Speaker 21: Oh. - And really just them each with themselves. They talk about a little bit, you know,
there's a...
In
Speaker 21: episode three, there's a little bit about PTSD where
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Tick tells Letty, hey, the whole haunted house thing, you went through some things, so maybe that's what you're manifesting here instead of believing that maybe the house was haunted. They did the same thing to Tick, though, in episode two when he was
Speaker 64: like, I saw things, and they were like, well, you were in the war. The way that PTSD is used as an excuse or to justify behavior that nobody wants to talk about...
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): And now that part of that part of blackness is is pretty prevalent. You know,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the folks just not talking about the issue and or calling it something else. Yeah. Or just not being honest about what things really are because, you
Man 60: know, you just don't talk about it. Yeah. So so that's that's a that's a huge thing that that we'll probably see, you know, kind of going forward.
Man 60: it tracks and
also for for for
Man 60: good storytelling you know that kind of thing you know tends to track as well uh what about you what what's been your favorite so far um all of it is
Speaker 147: scary so um what about from a historical aspect oh okay i'm
Speaker 33: glad you asked yeah well i mean all of it has been really good
from
Speaker 17: a historical perspective i think the the like deep cut of uh what was i think it was the holy ghost episode the third one when the kids are downstairs playing in the ouija board and that's when we find out that the kid
is both
Speaker 17: And he's like am I gonna have a good trip and the Ouija board immediately goes to no like snaps I mean, it doesn't even there's no like meandering. It just goes. No, and then people are kind of just like oh And I remember thinking I was like, why does that shirt look familiar? Yeah, so we know that the show is happening prior to August of 1955 or maybe it's at the beginning of August of 95 We just write
Speaker 124: something there. Yeah, but
Speaker 17: the thing that was really fascinating to me was that Misha Green mentioned that
Speaker 39: during the like exorcism
in
Speaker 39: the house right because like Hiram is the is the medical dude who basically kidnaps the reanimator yeah he kidnaps people to like do experiments on black bodies which has been a thing for fucking ever um sorry mom but
Speaker 35: that one deserved a cuss word but then realizing that some of the names that were being called out when Leti was like bringing in the memory of these people to help exercise this like bad spirit from the house were actually names of enslaved people yes like that that I was like oh
Speaker 35: okay okay yeah misha yeah look right look i'm gonna need you to not also please keep going right right because that was that was the thing that was like okay i can keep watching this because the history nerd in me was like
ah i want
Speaker 35: more what will she do next right but
Speaker 155: then the like fearful person in me is like i don't want to do this so like i watched with like my eyes closed but also like with one one eye slightly squinted yeah because i wanted to see more but it also speaks
Speaker 39: to like the generational trauma that is
Speaker 39: carried in certain spaces, like certain spaces hold a lot of weight, you know, in February, I was able to go to Money, Mississippi and see Bryant's grocery and how like dilapidated it is. And in 2017, when I went for the first time and witnessed
Speaker 39: kind of and just was able to see the story that like everything that happened to Emmett Till like kind of the starting point of it was. There was a black
Speaker 17: gentleman who was maybe in his 60s around that time and he literally said like he just we just happened to come up on him you know leading a different group
Speaker 39: and he said you know I live down the street from from Moe's right Emmett Till's great uncle
and
Speaker 39: the thing that's crazy is like
Speaker 17: nobody told us what happened. It wasn't until I was in my 40s that I found out what happened. And on top of that, he said all we knew is our principal told us that we were not supposed to go to that store anymore. And not only, and there's literally like another little store like right next to it. And he said every time we walked past Bryant's grocery, it felt weird. Like a cold shiver would pass through us. And I was like, yo, these locations in
which
Speaker 17: immense trauma has happened to black people. They hold memories. I fully believe that ancestors, spirits, whatever you want to call it, but like locations hold memories. And so for me, like the ghost aspect of that show, that episode was like scary obviously 'cause
like,
The
Speaker 17: animators or the graphic people did a really good job. But also from a historical perspective, I was like, oh, this is like this happened to people. And I think that for white people watching the show and also like with Watchmen, there's these moments where white people are like, well, I mean, they probably just added this in for the sake of the shock value. And then for black people watching it, they're like, no, this was...
Speaker 17: "real life for my ancestors. "Had some of my ancestors not survived "some of these really horrific
Speaker 39: things, "I would not be here." And so for Leti to use and invoke the names of the people from the past, and for her to be the one who was so passionate about
Speaker 47: figuring out how to release these spirits, and yeah, she was scared, but it wasn't like she was scared because these people were
Speaker 17: trying to get her. Well, I think at first she was. She was like, "I don't really understand."
But
Speaker 17: I also kind of thought of it like they were trying to get her attention. Yeah. Or maybe that's just what I told myself to not be scared.
Speaker 46: Well, there was at some point where the – because she was told to get out. You could hear it. There was a couple of times. Of course, there was that one scene where
Speaker 139: the figure came out of the pictures. Oh, I closed my eyes
Speaker 161: to that part. Cool.
So
Speaker 46: figure came out of the pictures.
I
Speaker 161: closed
Speaker 46: my eyes for that. But you heard that get out. You know what it made me think of, the old Eddie Murphy delirious.
Speaker 46: why
Speaker 162: don't white people just leave the house when there's a ghost in the house they walked and looked in the toilet bowl with blood in the toilet they said that's
Speaker 163: peculiar
Speaker 164: um joke where you know they they move it black people been moving to the house and he was like i would have
Speaker 165: been in the house and said oh baby this is beautiful we got a chandelier hanging up here kids outside playing it's a beautiful neighborhood being out in the world i really love them this is really nice get
out too
Speaker 166: bad we can't stay baby
And
Speaker 166: I left. But, you know, with Letty,
Speaker 21: she wasn't having it. You know, I mean, part of that, I think, you know, could have been pride to just the fact that she is Letitia fucking Lewis and she is not about to leave just because like...
Speaker 21: i've been through episode one and two like i've been through this is fine
Speaker 168: you know and i
Speaker 169: was with eustace hunt in the woods and had to run because i was a track star to go get the car and yeah i've yeah
Speaker 21: i've seen white people die
and
Speaker 21: monsters it's fine yeah this is
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): fine yeah so um and then to watch her then be the one to yet again save the day um by calling upon those spirits
Speaker 170: and saying no take it back
Speaker 171: take it back and she was
like get
Speaker 170: the fuck
Speaker 172: out of my house which was like i was like no
Speaker 172: And
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): then she finally decided to do, you know, do right by not only black folks, but by what her sister was talking to her about, you know, with using
Man 60: the house for, you know, for non selfish reasons. Yeah. You know, and so that was that was really dope.
Speaker 21: I don't really buy the. So you're telling me that all those people in the house and when it started, there were people outside, people arriving like it was packed.
Speaker 21: nobody saw a
Speaker 46: ghost a
Speaker 174: cross being burnt
like
Speaker 46: just that's like you could you saw a dude running away and i was like nobody nobody not until it started burning okay that's what's
up
Speaker 175: i mean in a white
Speaker 47: neighborhood the other white people were probably like oh john john the boys are bringing the cross oh okay martha let me walk over to the window and watch do you guys
Speaker 30: need a lighter no you good oh okay i'm talking about the people in the black house like nobody everybody
Speaker 177: was half drunk
Speaker 178: fam outside nothing they were drunk i'm just saying
but
Speaker 104: also also also also also that scene right like we saw letty do the whole like beyonce hold up oshun bat to car windows things right the thing that was so fascinating to me and so just like black was letty's sister got into the car because when she went to
Speaker 17: go
Speaker 31: smash the windows all like a couple of the black dudes came outside and shotguns to like watch her smash windows 'cause they were like, "Girl,
do what you gotta do."
Speaker 31: i got you and as soon as she was done smashing windows letty's sister got into her car
Speaker 17: pulled up they all put the guns in the trunk and she sped off do you and then the police officer showed up and they immediately got on their hands and knees and then put their hands up and then letty was put into the car with the uh chief police chief and that's where we got the term rough ride rough ride yep and so let you know the car the paddy wagon switch moves from side to side and a lot of black people have been very injured and also lost their lives with those quote-unquote rough rides
Speaker 180: which if you
Speaker 180: imagine like man back in 1950
Speaker 22: no 2016 yeah baltimore freddie gray yeah that's where you know it got a lot of it got a lot of traction people like rough like this wait this is a thing like oh my god yeah and um yeah it still happens um just like with sundown towns are still a thing yeah you
Speaker 21: know it's
Speaker 21: white people have a really whiteness has a really hard time letting go of the things
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): that kept them structurally in power and so this that's why i believe that lacene
Speaker 182: kansas is a sundown town unsolved mysteries alonzo brown we'll find out what happened
Speaker 77: so black women and black twitter will assist yeah um
But
Speaker 77: yeah, you're right.
Speaker 21: That was very... It was very...
How to
Speaker 21: survive whiteness. Chapter 6, paragraph 7. And, you know,
Speaker 74 (lower-pitched voice): when cops arrive, someone should get in a car, back it into the driveway, put the shotguns in the truck. The whole thing, it was
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): seamless. There wasn't... There was no instructions. Exactly. It was very much...
Speaker 66 (lower-pitched voice): walking past a black person on the street in the head nod
Speaker 64: yeah yeah it was very much that everybody just knew exactly what needed to happen because it was a conversation this is the conversation that
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): happens at our dinner tables yeah you know and and so and so oh this is the thing got it okay yeah and she was gone yeah man yeah and in the rough ride and as soon as soon as he as soon as he grabbed the strap oh i was like
Speaker 185: something that's about to happen yeah and the thing about it is
like
I
Speaker 17: think because I'm watching it with a black family and so there's this thing about like oh we kind of all are a little bit aware of like what's about to happen right and also it's really fun to watch it with black people because like the commentary is half of the best
Speaker 104: part oh he grabbed the thing he grabbed the thing oh my god right and so I think that what I'm hoping people get out
of
for
Speaker 15: you who haven't watched it yet or for you who are watching it and then listen to this episode and then go back and like watch it again because you're like oh i hadn't thought of that i hope folks start to really look into like the history
Speaker 39: that the show was trying to show you because for whatever reason america doesn't want to admit that like bad shit
Speaker 17: happened in this country we want to focus on like what we're doing now also um the cheeto and president uh is out here talking about we can't you know federal
Speaker 39: government or federal agencies can't teach and like diversity You can't do diversity training.
Speaker 39: He's going to defund schools that use the 1619 Project to talk about racism. And then I just it's so fascinating to me because you have countries like Germany, which the Holocaust was horrible. Also, Hitler learned a bunch of stuff that he did to Jewish folks from American racism. Yes. And also, you know, apartheid in South
Speaker 17: Africa who have engaged in these really like.
Speaker 17: Thoughtful ways of reconciliation of like talking about like okay. This history was really shitty a group of us did really really bad Things right other group. Let's like talk about it
Speaker 115: acknowledge it and then move forward as a unit where America's like slavery No, those are just Negroes out in the fields working like they just you know, they frolicked
Speaker 104: up until 1970s books were saying the Negroes would have a barbecue After a day out into the fields like I mean not know
Speaker 187: the Negroes were being barbecued and
on
Speaker 17: the field
Speaker 187: the fields
Speaker 17: and so i think that what i'm hoping that shows like watchmen and you know lovecraft country is like you can't escape this racism that is
Speaker 15: part of your heritage that is part of the heritage of this country and
even in
Speaker 15: the first episode where they're in the sun downtown and the sheriff eustace hunt which first of all i had never
Speaker 104: met a racist name more racist
Speaker 152: than eustace hunt if your name is eustace i apologize but also like it just bees like that His name was Yuck.
Speaker 152: eustace hunt he looks like the epitome of a racist sheriff and the like the like the chasing scene right
Speaker 189: it's at three we gotta pass the train tracks well
thomas it's
Speaker 189: uh it's uh
Speaker 190: 707 05 can
Speaker 191: we make it in four minutes
Speaker 190: we have to
right they were going
Speaker 110: 25 miles an hour i was like this is the most intense slow chase scene and then i was like oh
Speaker 104: the feeling that i'm feeling that they're depicting is what i feel when there's a cop car behind me every
Speaker 192: time lights are not on every single time but
Speaker 17: it's like oh my goodness i had to tell this white woman who decided to tell me that not all cops are bad and bless her heart because i had a good day that day and so i didn't read her for filth 'cause I was about to. But I had to tell her, I said,
Speaker 17: use cruise control for and she was like what do you mean and i was like do you use your cruise control and she was like i mean not really and i was like i use cruise control so that i stay within the speed limit so i don't get pulled over so i don't die
and she just she oh and i was
Speaker 17: like so don't tell like don't don't come at me yeah like it
Speaker 17: i'm not here for it yeah and so that like little like five minute
Speaker 194: clip and then the worst part is like they got over the line and i was like yeah they
Speaker 195: made it man literally
Speaker 194: the music got a little better and then like
Speaker 20: 10 seconds later i was like nah bitch they didn't
make it
Speaker 20: the whole show is just palpitations
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): palpitations but so fun it could be so fun to watch um again it just i
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): love seeing
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): These characters doing things that we have seen just dominated by
Speaker 21: white spaces, heroes of the day and solving solving puzzles while the plank is disappearing
Speaker 64: underneath you. And just reading, reading, they mention books so much so often.
Speaker 64: Like, just books on books and books. And, like, there's a scene
in
Speaker 178: the library. That little boy was like, if you don't shut up,
Speaker 17: I'm
Speaker 196: tired
of
Speaker 17: y'all. I'm just trying to read. Yeah. I think the beauty of the show is the plethora of ways
Speaker 39: black people are awesome. And also the honesty...
in
Speaker 39: the way black people are tortured just for wanting a better life for themselves and i commend absolutely misha green um for the brilliance that is in the subtlety of the like really sweet moments um like with uncle george and his wife uh
Speaker 17: hippolyta which btw that's wonder woman's mom's name so we're gonna see what happens with her because she knows some
Speaker 180: shit is up first off i I mean, she's going to do her thing, but she took a whole...
Speaker 180: Again, like with the cross-brand. How do you
Speaker 198: remove
Speaker 199: an entire solar system? And
Speaker 198: nobody knew. Nobody. Whatever alcohol was in that picture that Letty was walking around with must have
Speaker 201: been strong. That orange, sunny
Speaker 46: D looking with the good. Also,
Speaker 200: did you realize that that was one shot?
-
Speaker 46: No, but yes, now that you say something,
Speaker 200: yes. - Yeah, when you watch that whole scene
Speaker 202: of her like walking around with the picture, it's just, it's one shot.
Speaker 59: - I love when they do that, I love when they do that. -
Speaker 185: They get that in Black
Speaker 59: Panther? - Yeah. - Sorry. - Yeah, I love it, I love it, I love
Speaker 185: it. - So we'll see, we'll see what happens with the next couple episodes. I'm sure, you know, some episodes down the line we'll
Speaker 33: do another like four episode or
Speaker 55: five episode recap, 'cause Lovecraft is bananas in pajamas. -
Yeah.
Speaker 55: And I'm going to go sage when I get home just
Speaker 204: to. You'll be all
Speaker 205: right. You'll be all right. Yeah, just to
Speaker 204: make sure that my ancestors are okay with me invoking.
They're
Speaker 206: fine. No need to slice any. First
of
Speaker 42: all, my great-grandmother. Oh, I ain't slicing shit. First of all, I'm not. Yikes. That was. That was a scene.
Speaker 42: we could just this
Speaker 22: might as well happen
for real
Speaker 22: like what else when and then the fact that they didn't even really flinch when she
just put an x
Speaker 22: of blood goat's blood on their
Speaker 207: foreheads also did she die
who
Speaker 208: the the
Speaker 207: sorcerers the kind of the
Speaker 208: voodoo yeah because the
Speaker 207: spirit of hyrum went into
Speaker 209: her and then she started choking uh she started choking tick
Speaker 210: but it came out of
Speaker 209: her and then went into tick but it came out of tick too we don't yeah we don't
Speaker 209: I'm sure she's
Speaker 211: probably fine She probably was like I don't think I want to do this anymore This is fine Anyway best
Speaker 213: of luck To you watching Best of luck Who did you put her two weeks into the spirits I don't
Speaker 214: know to that goat
Speaker 216: Oh damn
Speaker 215: Do they cook the meat goat meat Anyway let's just Thanks
Speaker 217: guys